<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of addresses in general, and of the Middle-Temple address and proceedings in particular in answer to the impartial account of addresses : wherein the popular pretences of some men are exposed / by a barrester of the Middle-Temple.</title>
            <author>Barrester of the Middle Temple.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65010</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V469</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18697</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12875515</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12875515</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94823</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65010)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94823)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 902:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of addresses in general, and of the Middle-Temple address and proceedings in particular in answer to the impartial account of addresses : wherein the popular pretences of some men are exposed / by a barrester of the Middle-Temple.</title>
                  <author>Barrester of the Middle Temple.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by N. Thompson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Middle Temple (London, England)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94823:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF Addreſſes in general, And of the <hi>Middle-Temple Addreſs</hi> and Proceedings in particular. In Anſwer to the <hi>Impartial Account of Addreſſes,</hi> wherein the Popular pretences of ſome men are expoſed. By a Barreſter of the <hi>Middle-Temple.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHen Faction and Ambition has ſeiz'd the Ignorant man, how troubleſom he grows? his Magiſterial Nonſence roars in every corner, fills every Preſs; and however nauſeous and intolerable it proves to the Diſcerning, yet the Vulgar too often admire the man, becauſe they underſtand him not, and are ready with him to cry out againſt the Government, for that He and ſuch Great men are not advanced thereto: Till at laſt the braying Animal brings both himſelf and his miſerable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded crowd, to the hazard of both their Temporal and Spiritual Intereſt. On ſuch men there was never greater cauſe of complaint, than now; and I wiſh to God the people would open their eyes, to ſee what theſe Incendiaries aim at. Has any man been Executed by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Authority illegally? Does not every man peaceably enjoy the Fruits of his own Vine? Are Liberties abridg'd in any one particular? or are any of theſe things like to be? Has not His Majeſty given freſh promiſes for the continuity of all and every theſe particulars, in his late moſt gracious Declaration? that's true, but that ſtabs them to the heart. 'Tis not the preſervation of the Lives, Liberties and Properties of the people, that theſe men ſeek; but they themſelves would be diſpoſers thereof. Wherefore their Choler boils mightily, that His Majeſty ſhould condeſcend to undeceive his people, but much more that a great part of the people ſhould be undeceived, and give His Majeſty thanks for that gracious condeſcention. This reduces them to their former ſneaking Aſpects, makes them ſtand as uneaſie, change feet as often as an Elephant learning to dance upon hot Stones. At laſt (theſe diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are plaguy things) out creeps a Treaſonable <hi>Anſwer to the Kings Declaration,</hi> which has been by ſome Loyal Pen moſt ingeniouſly reflected on; After that, <hi>An Impartial Account</hi> (as 'tis titled) <hi>of the Nature and Tendency of the late Addreſſes;</hi> and this o' my word is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed after no ordinary rate, not by one, I dare ſay, that pretends to thoſe little helps and tricks of Unriverſity and Humane Learning: No, no, by one of the Saints of our times, who's above the vain thing called Learning, or the dull thing called Practical Divinity. Gratitude! What paid to the King too! This is in its nature the moſt devilliſh thing that ever was found out. But ſuppoſe the Commons do give His Majeſty thanks for his gracious Speeches made to them in Parliament; this is one argument that they don't think Addreſſing or giving His Majeſty thanks, a thing evil in its own nature: If not, the next Parliament no doubt will be for maintaining the Liberties of the Subject, and proceed againſt thoſe as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayers of our Liberties, who have declared Addreſſes to be evil in their nature. This we may well ſupp ſe from that late inſtance of preſerving the Right of Petitioning; and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing being altogether as great a Right, it will no doubt receive as great favour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection from the Parliament. Well, perhaps the nature of Gratitude is not truly ſo black as it does appear to our Authors Conſcience; what then? 'Tis however a vain inſignificant
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94823:2"/>thing, and a thing of as damnable tendency as any thing about the Town: For confirmation of this, there's a huge bundle of Reaſons, which had never never ſeen day had it not been for <hi>pure love and compaſſion</hi> (p. 4. §. 1.) <hi>to the King, whom he fears is not only induſtriouſly deluded, but wofully betray'd, by the Judgment which ſome about him pretend to make of the ſence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the people from theſe Addreſſes.</hi> Ah love and compaſſion! how I reverence love and compaſſion! what condition were we tumbling into, till you <hi>Ah love and compaſſion</hi> rais'd this <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſtand in the gap! till you made him in all humility let the Privy-Councel know they were Fools and Knaves, and in all humility let His Majeſty know what an object of pity He was become, by his unreaſonable credulity.</p>
            <p>And now woe to the poor Addreſſers, for out comes our Authors Reaſons: the firſt is to be found in p. 4. <hi>No applications of this nature to the Regnant perſon, are to be eſteemed of any great weight and ſignificancy, if you do but conſider the reſult of the many Addreſſes</hi> 23 <hi>years ago to</hi> Richard Cromwell, <hi>and how they only ſerved to render him ſecure, till he was undermined and ſupplanted; for of all that vowed to live and dye by him, not ſo much as one man drew a Sword in his favour, when he came to be laid aſide.</hi> That is as much as to ſay, May it pleaſe your Majeſty, I as in tender love and compaſſion bound, do in all humility let your Majeſty know, that your Majeſty is a poor deluded wretch, and cannot ſee ſo far into a Mill-ſtone as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, elſe you would never eſteem thoſe ill-look'd things called Addreſſes. Alas! every Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant perſon is to believe all his Subjects deceitful and lying Rogues, he is to give credit to nothing they vow and proteſt; becauſe the Whigs proved Lyars to <hi>Richard Cromwell,</hi> and notwithſtanding their Addreſſes, when they ſaw the rightful perſon would prevail, they left poor <hi>Dick</hi> in the lurch. In ſhort, the Argument is this; If the Whigs are Lyars and not to be truſted, all the men in the World are Lyars and not to be truſted: But the Whigs are Lyars and not to be truſted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Aſſumption is proved, and it's no great matter for proving the Major; beſides he's juſt now when he ſhould go about it, p. 5. frighted into the moſt aſtoniſhing, ſurprizing, amazing fit, that ever poor creature was. Strange! what will this Age come to, when well-meaning men are thus ſcared out of their ſenſes? The reaſon of this wondering fit is to be ſeen at large in p. 5. <hi>viz.</hi> That His Majeſty ſhould more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance one who comes to reprehend and inſtruct him in his managements in State-affairs, than one who is well pleaſed with His Majeſties managements, and for that reaſon comes to make his humble and grateful acknowledgments. If this is not cauſe of wonder, what is? eſpecially when we conſider too, as 'tis in the ſaid. p. That Petitioners know what they want, but Addreſſers do not know what's promiſed to them, or what they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Moreover and above, <hi>Addreſſes will not,</hi> p. 8. <hi>in the event prove ſo uſefull either to a Popiſh or Arbitrary deſign, as ſome do apprehend:</hi> No, I think verily that is very needleſly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; <hi>Not that any think the King knows of ſuch a deſign promoted by them, but there are thoſe who may have ends in this, which His Majeſty is not aware of.</hi> What a happy Nation ſhould we be, had His Majeſty but this man's Head-piece! then there would be ſome hopes that he would love and embrace thoſe mightily that always ſhewed an uneaſineſs under his Government, and as much diſcountenance thoſe who came to give him thanks for, and were well pleaſed with what He did. I, then the King would ſee, that for his Subjects to be well pleaſed with his actions, was always a Popiſh and Arbitrary deſign; but 'twas They were his Friends, who were always rendring both his perſon and actions contemptible and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous. He would then ſee, §. 4. <hi>that Addreſſes tend only to divide the Nation into Faction and Parties: but that Petitions had no ſuch tendency.</hi> 'Tis true, the Petitioners began before the Addreſſers, and had given the ſtamp of Papiſt, and Popiſhly affected, upon all Non Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: What they call that, I can't tell, but 'twas not dividing, for that was for Petitions; and would any man think that Petitioning would divide the Nation, therefore 'twas not dividing, but for Addreſſing, any man may ſee that divides the Nation, therefore that is dividing. To proceed, His Majeſty would then ſee that, §. 7. <hi>the number of Addreſſers are very few, all of them put together makes not ſo great number as we have ſeen not long ſince to one Petition.</hi> Well ſaid Whig, this is a Swinger! let the Reader take notice, this is a ſecond proof that Whigs will lye: If this be true, where was the need of our Author's tender care and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion towards His Majeſty, in rectifying the apprehenſion of Him and his Privy-Councel concerning the ſence of the Nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for they have the numbers before them both of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſers and Petitioners, and they could not therefore be deceived which was greateſt. Our Author ſeems to miſtruſt this will not be ſwallowed, therefore adds, p. 10. <hi>If it be allowed, as in juſtice as well as modeſty it ought, that whoever have either avoided or refuſed ſubſcribing; are as truly to be judg'd againſt them, as they who have poſitively withſtood, or directly oppoſed them, then the tale of the Addreſſers will make but a very ſmall ſhew and appearance in the Muſter-Roll of the Nation.</hi> Smartly ſaid, I proteſt! Muſt it not as well follow that they who avoided or refuſed ſubſcribing Petitions, are as truly to be judg'd againſt them, as they who have poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94823:2"/>withſtood, or directly oppoſed them? And then what a ſhow they will make in the Muſter-Roll of the Nation. And now the Gentleman is fallen into a fit of railing for two or three pages together; <hi>That the Addreſſers are the ſcum of the people; Thoſe which are Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly inclined,</hi> &amp;c. All which I deny, ſo there wants only proof on his part: And thus he concludes his natural thoughts, as to the general; and I begin mine as follows: That to give His Majeſty Thanks for His late moſt Gracious <hi>Declaration,</hi> is very avowable; for my firſt reaſon, I ſhall lay down theſe two Propoſitions, <hi>That grateful acknowledgments for favours received, are a Christians Duty; That for every man to be judge when he has received a favour, is an</hi> Engliſh <hi>mans Liberty.</hi> One would think neither of theſe two Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions need any manner of proof; But becauſe thoſe who would be thought the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers of our Liberties are for betraying them; in this, or any other particular, where they run counter to their Damnable Deſigns, (of which, no doubt, the next Parliament will take notice) I ſhall prove the ſecond Propoſition from their own practices, I mean Petitioning; for if I have not a liberty of judging what is a Favour when received, <hi>à fortiori,</hi> I have no liberty of judging what will be a Favour when it ſhall be received, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then at a greater diſtance; therefore leſs capable of judging; So that by conſequence if they do except to what I have laid down <hi>a fortiori,</hi> they muſt exclude themſelves the Right of Petitioning: Wherefore I may conclude, if I do not diſlike the Kings Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe 'tis the Kings, or becauſe 'twas given with an intent to ſatisfie the Minds of His Subjects, but really do eſteem it as a Gracious Favour, (notwithſtanding theſe and ſuch like weighty reaſons) I may, nay I am bound, as appears by my firſt Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to render His Majeſty all Humble Thanks. Wherefore in ſo doing, I am ſo far from breaking, that I keep the Law.</p>
            <p>But I need not take this advantage, that becauſe I think the King's <hi>Declaration</hi> exacts Thanks, therefore I may juſtifie paying them; For I may well ſtand the Tryal, whether right reaſon does not call upon us to perform that reſpect as a duty; and in order thereto, I ſhall reduce the King's <hi>Declaration</hi> to theſe three Heads. 1ſt. His Reaſons for His diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving two Parliaments, <hi>2dly.</hi> His promiſes to govern according to <hi>Law. 3dly.</hi> His promiſes to call frequent Parliaments. Firſt, His Reaſons for diſſolving two Parliaments! The very naming of this Head is ſufficient to baffle that blundring miſtake of thoſe that affirm, that when we give His Majeſty Thanks in general for His <hi>Declaration,</hi> we give him Thanks for diſſolving two Parliaments; As if there was no difference between diſſolving, and giving reaſons for diſſolving: Thoſe Diſſolutions were unqueſtionably juſtifiable by Law: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, the King condeſcends to give us reaſons; For what? for doing a thing which by Law he might do. This was certainly more than His Greatneſs need to have condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended to, and therefore commands our grateful returns: eſpecially if we conſider the end for what 'twas done, which does fully appear to be only for the quiet and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his Subjects minds, at ſuch a time, when Male-Contents were endeavouring to poſſeſs the people with a <hi>needleſs</hi> Fear and Jealouſie, that theſe Diſſolutions were in order to their utter Ruin and Deſtruction. <hi>2dly.</hi> Our Thanks are due, for His Majeſties gracious promiſe, That he will govern according to <hi>Law.</hi> This grave Mr. <hi>Thompſon</hi> (glad, no doubt, of the opportunity) explodes, in a formal Speech before the Bench of the <hi>Middle-Temple,</hi> upon the account of the <hi>Addreſs</hi> carrying on in that Society; ſays that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, (a weighty reaſon truly) <hi>The King is bound by his Coronation-Oath to govern accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Laws of the Land, therefore in ſo doing he does but his duty, and 'tis abſurd to thank any man for barely doing his duty.</hi> I can't ſay theſe are the words, but I am mis-informed if this be not the ſubſtance of Mr. <hi>Thompſon</hi>'s Argument; which in form is thus: <hi>Whenever a man does but his bare duty, 'tis abſurd to pay him Thanks for ſo doing: But the King has done but his duty,</hi> &amp;c. He had done well, had he proved the major Propoſition. 'Tis but the bare duty of every rich man, to relieve one whom he knows to be neceſſitous; 'Tis but the bare duty of every Chriſtian, when he ſees another almoſt ſuffocated in a Pit, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>end the utmoſt aſſiſtance to his relief; 'Tis but the bare duty of a Father, (which is juſt the caſe) to provide for, and comfort his Children; But none can be ſo hardy to deny Thanks to be due in all theſe caſes; wherefore that Argument is groſly Illogical. And further, let me ask, why the City, and ſome Countreys, gave Thanks to their Members that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Parliament, for preſerving their right of Petitioning, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> Did theſe Members more than barely execute their Truſt, or more than what was barely their Duty? When men catch hold of ſtraws, 'tis ſign they're ſinking. Our Author (§ 12.) inſiſts upon the ſame reaſon, but goes ſomewhat further; For, (ſays he) <hi>It does unbecome</hi> Engliſh <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to thank their Prince for promiſing to govern according to Law, ſeeing, as he never did, ſo cannot do otherwiſe.</hi> Let it be admitted; But then, why all this roaring againſt his Royal Highneſs? By what means can He take our Lives, Liberties, and Properties? By
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94823:3"/>what means can He introduce <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> if a King cannot do otherwiſe than go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern according to <hi>Law?</hi> This is down-right confeſſing they ſcare the people, when there's no need for't <hi>3dly.</hi> Beyond all contradiction, His Majeſty may juſtly expect our Thanks, for his promiſe of frequent Parliaments; why elſe was there ſuch a ſtir made in petitioning for them? It may well be preſumed, thoſe men were not in earneſt, when they ſeemed hotly and zealouſly to deſire, and now they have a gracious promiſe, that their deſires ſhall be fulfilled, think that promiſe not worth their acknowledgements. From what has been ſaid, 'tis manifeſt, 1ſt. That, admit His Majeſties Declaration does not reaſonably exact Thanks, yet, if any man thinks it does, he (being thereof proper Judge) is obliged to pay them. <hi>2dly.</hi> That there is not one particular in that <hi>Declaration,</hi> but what, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to right reaſon, exacts our moſt grateful returns. As for the particular forms of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes, which our Author quotes, I am not obliged to juſtifie, not only becauſe I have them not by me, and therefore cannot know whether He prevaricates, but alſo becauſe ſeveral paſſages in theſe forms are incerted upon reaſons moſt obvious to the Inhabitants of that place from whence they came: For in one place the Republican-ſpirits take one way in another, another way according as they and the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> together think moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to their ends; Wherefore each company of Loyal Addreſſers aſſure His Majeſty to ſtand by him, in oppoſition to thoſe undutiful Managements, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which they more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly ſee carried on. I ſhall therefore ſay nothing to any particular form, except that of the <hi>Middle-Temple,</hi> to which I was a Subſcriber. And before I ſpeak to the exception againſt the Addreſs it ſelf, becauſe there has been a great noiſe made, as if our Proceedings in the carrying it on were abominably irregular, I ſhall acquaint the world with the truth of the fact, as follows: At the firſt propoſing of an Addreſs, 'twas thought fit to appoint a meeting at a <hi>Tavern,</hi> that they might conſider whether their Party were the Majority, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would publickly propoſe it in the <hi>Hall:</hi> Upon this ſcore they met two or three times, which begot a Jealouſy in the Adverſe party (who alſo met, and I ſuppoſe too, 'twas to try their own ſtrength,) that we would huddle up an Addreſs, and privately get Hands, without propoſing the matter fairly and publickly in the <hi>Hall.</hi> To this effect I have heard our Party upbraided, who ſtill replyed they deſigned no ſuch thing, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed did they: But a day was appointed, and the fulleſt <hi>Hall</hi> that has been ſeen appeared. We made a noiſe for one Speaker, they for another; we with all the earneſtneſs ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable preſt a Poll; twice or oftner we drew out from them in order thereto, yet could not obtain it. When they would by no means come to a Poll, we took it for granted they yielded us the Majority (and indeed we were ſo) we ſet our Speaker in the Chair, who put the Queſtion, and all that Voted him Speaker, Voted for the Addreſs. After this was all over, and a great many of us gone, ſome of the other party very Gravely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a Poll. No ſooner were we all gone, then they choſe themſelves a Speaker, Voted our Proceeding Irregular <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For that we had no power to call a Parliament in Term time, the <hi>Benchers</hi> having then the ſole Government of the Houſe: They cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured likewiſe that we had appointed three of the Clock, but met at two, ſo that their party was ſurpriz'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus truly ſtands the Fact; I defie any of them to prove me miſtaken in any one particular. And now I ſhall beg leave to make ſome brief Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That they were ſurpriz'd by our appointing Three of the Clock, and our meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Two, is totally falſe; for they knew the time of meeting as well as we our ſelves, and they had publick notice thereof by the Blowing of the Horn: There was divers of their party preſent (I knew none Abſent) at the very time of our Meeting, which had not been in Commons within twelve Months at leaſt; abundance that had not been in Commons that Term, and how was it poſſible for thoſe to be there, had they not had fair notice? Nor was this Sham ever mention'd, till they found themſelves the fewer number. <hi>2dly.</hi> 'Tis very obſervable that they ſhould upbraid us for not meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing publickly in the <hi>Hall,</hi> (which I will Depoſe I heard,) and then becauſe we did meet publickly in the <hi>Hall,</hi> that they ſhould Vote our Proceedings Irregular. Which way ſhall one take to pleaſe ſuch men? There was no noiſe of Irregular proceedings in the <hi>Inner Houſe</hi> when 'twas, carried (though in Term time) againſt the Addreſs: Nay, to my own knowledge, not long ſince: Theſe very men who now Vote our Proceedings Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, becauſe the <hi>Bench</hi> are the governing part in Term; theſe very men, I mean all the Leading men were the moſt buſie Actors in our Parliaments conven'd in Term-time, even in oppoſition to the <hi>Bench:</hi> In anſwer to theſe inſtances they tell us; thoſe Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments began in Vacation, and therefore they might continue them in Term: What a miſerable ſhift thoſe Gentlemen are put to, to vent ſuch Nonſenſe for their excuſes? As if our calling a Parliament in Vacation, took away the <hi>Benchers</hi> power in Term. Had
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94823:3"/>they not much better deal plainly and ſay, that Parliaments which meet in Term in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the <hi>Bench</hi> are well enough, becauſe they favour ſomething like Rebellion: But Parliaments that meet to carry on Addreſſes, thoſe, fye upon'm irregular things! They are never to be juſtified, for they look ſomething like Loyalty: To come yet harder upon theſe Gentlemen; If becauſe the Government is in the <hi>Bench,</hi> we have no power to act Parliamentary: Firſt, why did they Nominate and Vote for a Speaker, if 'twas an Irregular meeting, why did they not oppoſe all Speakers? No, if their party had been ſtrong enough to have carried it, all had been extreamly Regular. But <hi>2dly.</hi> By what Authority did they themſelves act Parliamentary when we were gone out of the <hi>Hall?</hi> By what Authority I ſay, did they chuſe a Speaker, Vote our Proceedings Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This was one of Neateſt compoſed Blunders that I ever met with: I have heard of one that would Swear bloodily all Swearers were damn'd; I have heard of a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> in a Conventicle bitterly railing againſt the Whore of <hi>Babylon:</hi> But now theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ceaſe to be Comical, they are far out-done: 'Tis a ſign the Well-meaning Party had all the underſtanding men (as they boaſted) of their ſide, for none but profound Conſidering men could be hotly condemning, what at the ſame time they were hotly practiſing: Upon the whole, I think it may be concluded that our proceedings are fully juſtified by even the Practices of our Oppoſers. There remains nothing therefore now, but to remove the Objection againſt the Addreſs it ſelf, which lyes <hi>p.</hi> 33. againſt theſe words, <hi>That we will Serve His Majeſty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>againſt thoſe who under ſpecious pretences, and by poſſeſſing the people with groundleſs Fears and Jealouſies, would bring us back into Anarchy and Confuſion. Surely,</hi> ſays my Author, <hi>had theſe perſons who preſume to ſuggeſt this unto His Majeſty, known any Republicans or Phanaticks who did do this, they ought by their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to have depoſed againſt them, and given in their Names that they might be Proſecuted.</hi> Depoſed againſt a Phanatick! any thing good Sir, any thing but that, there's a Notion indeed at this time a day; when there muſt be more Witneſſes to ſatisfie even a <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> when the Bill is againſt one of them, then is required at <hi>Rome</hi> to Convict a <hi>Cardinal:</hi> Now, 'tis but Herding with the Godly Conſcientious party, and you may commence Rogue with ſafety; for you muſt know they are our Jury-men, and 'tis beneath thoſe <hi>Saints</hi> to be guided by the old Fuſty Rules of <hi>doing as you would be done unto;</hi> of doing Juſtice equally, without Favour or Affection. Alas! there are Crutches fit only for weak Brethren to bear on, fit for thoſe only who have not arrived to their pitch of Godlineſs. There's nothing guides them but their Conſciences, and their Conſciences can, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their Oaths to the contrary,) find one Guilty without Evidence, another Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, though there be many Credible Witneſſes to the contrary. Verily, verily, theſe men were i'th right on't when they only ask'd Liberty of Conſcience; had they but Liberty of Conſcience, the Devil were an Aſs if he put them upon asking more: Did we therefore know how 'twould be in vain to Depoſe againſt the Sanctified Crew: But it does not follow (by the Gentlemans leave) that I cannot have a Moral certainty that Diſcord and Rebellion are the ends of theſe mens Actions, and yet not be able to bring them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a laſh by Depoſing. For firſt, this may be done by <hi>Mediums,</hi> which come under no Law, yet as they are circumſtantiated, do manifeſtly tend to, or at leaſt are aim'd at no other ends: <hi>2dly.</hi> If their <hi>Medium</hi> do come under a Law, as by Treaſonable Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they are pleaſed to let us have them without Names, ſo that it would be very difficult, without the help of one of our late Grand-Jury mens Conſciences to Depoſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively againſt any particular perſon: I ſay this may be done firſt by <hi>Mediums</hi> which come under no Law, yet as they are circumſtantiated, do manifeſtly tend to, or at leaſt are arriv'd at no other end. And theſe are principally three. 1ſt. Petitioning for Parliaments. <hi>2dly.</hi> Their deſires of a Bill of Excluſion. <hi>3dly.</hi> Their Fears of the Popiſh-plot: They themſelves don't think that any one of theſe three things come under any Law; therefore whether they do or not, I need not inquire, but demonſtrate, that every one of theſe particulars as manag'd by them, I ſay, as manag'd by them, are deſigned means to raiſe ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Fears and Jealouſies among the people; and then as I before obſerved, what ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies Depoſing in ſuch Caſes: To begin with the firſt Petitioning for Parliaments, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty was made ſenſible what they would Petition for, and ſhewed His diſlike thereto by publick Proclamation, yet ſtill did they obtrude Petitions for the ſame things: And what could be the meaning of ſuch Rudeneſs and ill Manners? No hopes of Succeſs, thoſe were all Anticipated by the Proclamation: But this vehement repeated Petitioning would ſerve to breed groundleſs Fears, that Ruine hung over the peoples Heads, and His Majeſty would not ſee it, that He was wholly regardleſs of His Peoples Welfare and Safety; whereas the people cannot be either Injur'd or Ruin'd, but the King muſt be ſo too. If this undoubted Truth were well conſidered, 'twould be enough to diſſipate all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94823:4"/>Jealouſies of His Majeſties Managements. But to return, why all this Fondneſs for Parliaments? What evil have they done that theſe men Satyr them with their good words? Does none Reverence Parliaments but <hi>Phanaticks?</hi> If Reverence be beſt ſeen by Obedience to Acts of Parliament, I am certain there are thoſe that pay greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects then Diſſenters, though with leſs noiſe. Could an Act of Parliament keep them from Conventicles? Could an Act bring them to Church? Could an Act keep them any diſtance from Corporations? Could an Act hinder them from Scribling Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Rebellious Principles? No, all Acts are but Cobwebs when they in the leaſt competize with the Intereſts or Inclinations of their party: And therefore, which brings me to the ſecond plauſible pretence, a Bill of Excluſion according to their own Tenents cannot be an Expedient for the Kingdoms Safety; for how can they, who barely for the ſake of unreaſonable Whimſeys trample upon Acts of Parliament, believe the Duke would be concluded by an Act in ſo great and weighty a matter, They will not object ſurely; That his Royal Highneſs is a better Subject than themſelves; one more conformable to Laws; No, they proclaim him <hi>a rigid Papiſt,</hi> and that no Laws can bind a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> when they come in Competition with the good of the Church. Upon this very reaſon they ſeem to preſs a <hi>Bill of Excluſion.</hi> No Laws, ſay they, can bind a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor, That</hi> (ſays the Character of a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor</hi>) <hi>is hedging in the Cuckow.</hi> Well then, a <hi>Bill of Excluſion</hi> would come in Competition with the good of his Church, or not; If not, then his Royal Highneſs being upon the Throne would be no advantage to his Church; then where's the fear of <hi>Popery?</hi> If it would, according to themſelves, his Royal Highneſs would not deem ſuch a Law obligatory; and then they cannot believe the Peace and Quiet of the Nation would be the conſequence of ſuch a Bill, but rather War and Confuſion; And 'tis that they would have; they care not which way they obtain it, whether by paſſing that Law, or whether by ſowing Sedition, rendring the King His Subjects dreadful Enemy, for not paſſing ſuch a Law. One ſecond hit for the Biſhops fair Poſſeſſions would mightily revive the hungry Saints.</p>
            <p>The 3d. plauſible pretence is, fears of a <hi>Popiſh-Plot;</hi> which was a <hi>Plot</hi> againſt His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Sacred Perſon, the preſent Government, and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion:</hi> We ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly therefore inquire into theſe three things: Firſt, Whether <hi>Phanaticks</hi> deſire His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Life more heartily than all the reſt of His more Loyal Subjects; or indeed, more than His Majeſty Himſelf? <hi>2dly.</hi> Whether they are the chief perſons aim'd at by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,</hi> when their <hi>Plots</hi> are laid againſt the <hi>Proteſtant Religion? 3dly.</hi> Whether They are the only perſons who would protect and preſerve the preſent Government? Firſt, That <hi>Phanaticks</hi> deſire His Majeſty's life, more than He does Himſelf, is wonderfully cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible; or that they value it more than the Loyal Party, is almoſt as credible; for the Queſtion is no more than this: Whether thoſe who have <hi>Martyr'd</hi> the late King, and uſed their utmoſt endeavour to <hi>Martyr</hi> This, be more zealous for the <hi>Preſervation</hi> of His Majeſties Life, than thoſe who to their utmoſt have aſſiſted His late Majeſty and this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King, in all times of dreadful Tryals and Adverſities? The deciſion of this Queſtion I leave to any juſt man; and if it does appear that 'tis in reaſon to be ſuppoſed that the King is as willing to preſerve His own Life, as the <hi>Phanaticks</hi> are to <hi>Preſerve</hi> it; If 'tis in reaſon to be ſuppoſed that thoſe who have ventured upon all occaſions their own Lives and Fortunes for the preſervation of the King, covet preſervation of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Life, as much as thoſe who have hazarded their Lives and Fortunes to <hi>Deprive</hi> HIs Majeſty of His Life and Government; then it as reaſonably follows, that their over <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Care</hi> of His Majeſty's Life, which exceeds greatly in appearance, both the King and his Loyal Subjects are but Pretence and Sham. <hi>2dly.</hi> Whether <hi>Phanaticks</hi> are the chief perſons aim'd at by the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> when their <hi>Plots</hi> are laid againſt the <hi>Proteſtant Religion?</hi> One would believe by theſe mens over-buſtling and noiſe, that they were the only De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of the <hi>Proteſtant Faith;</hi> That 'twas only the Ruine of Them the <hi>Papiſts</hi> levell'd at, as a certain means to eradicate the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> Whereas <hi>Rome</hi> well knows, theſe men are a Goad in our Churches ſide, and therefore its Emiſſaries were careful to make and increaſe them: That the <hi>Papiſts</hi> made them out of meer envy to our incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Church, is evident from the Examinations of ſome <hi>Popiſh-Prieſts</hi> in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s time; The firſt was one <hi>Faithful Commin</hi> a Frier of the order of St <hi>Dominick:</hi> he made the firſt breach in our Churches walls, by railing againſt Forms of Prayer, calling the <hi>Engliſh-Prayers Engliſh-Maſs,</hi> perſwading people to pray <hi>Spiritually</hi> and <hi>Extempore;</hi> to whom the <hi>Pope</hi> gave a reward for his conſiderable Service. Two years after, one <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Heath a Jeſuit</hi> was taken acting the ſame part; which ſtories ſee at large in <hi>Foxes and Firebrands,</hi> Printed 1680. and in the Reverend Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Preface to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſs of Separation.</hi> But the <hi>Papists</hi> were not only careful to make, but ever ſince
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94823:4"/>conſtantly to increaſe Votaries to the Phanatick Party; to this end the Jeſuits have conſtantly preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e among the Conventiclers, to the Truth of this many can witneſs. And Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> has depoſed, nay when we preſs Phanaticks with their actions of 41. they tell us for Excuſe, they were deluded by the Papiſts: from which it fully appears, that 'tis againſt the Church of <hi>England</hi> all their Plots and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies are planted; So far from being aim'd primarily at Diſſenters, that the Papiſts do with all their Art endeavour to preſerve them as Inſtruments and Tools to afflict and overthrow us. From theſe Premiſſes I ſhall draw not unnaturally two Concluſions. Firſt, That thoſe declamatory Revilings the Phanaticks throw upon the Members of our Church, as being Popiſhly affected, are but bare-fac'd Lyes and Calumnies; for 'tis incredible the Papiſts would vent all their malice agaiſnt their Friends, and do what in them lies to cheriſh and increaſe their only Enemies, as the Nonconformiſts would have the World believe they are. Is it not the Proteſtant Religion Papiſts would extirpate? And can that be ſuppoſed a way which increaſes the preſervers thereof. Whatever theſe Diſſenters pretend, they cannot but know that this is too too abſurd; They cannot but know the Papiſts believe them the ſcandal and affliction to the true Profeſſors of the Proteſtant Religion, that they deſerve not the name of Proteſtant, for by <hi>Proteſtant</hi> is meant one who proteſts againſt the Errors only, not the Truths too of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> if other wiſe, a <hi>Turk</hi> may be called a <hi>Proteſtant:</hi> Is it not them the Papiſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid us with in all our Diſputations? Is it not amongſt them they ſhrowd in all their Helliſh pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices; nor had the Papiſts had any thing to ſay or do againſt the Proteſtant Religion, had it not been for the unhappy aſſiſtance given them by theſe fooliſh and wicked Diſſenters. A ſecond Concluſion is, That whatſoever reaſonable fear there is of execution of a Popiſh plot, it ought to be lodg'd in the breaſts of the Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they being only the marks and Butts of all the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſtratagems of the Papiſts. Wherefore when we ſee thoſe who have leaſt to loſe, Thoſe whom the Plot is leaſt aim'd at, the only men who ſeem to be ſcared and frighted out of their Senſes, the only men who roar out Murder, as if the knife were already at their throats, and that tho the Plot be defeated, it nothing at all abates their unreaſonable noiſe; what can a man conclude, but that this exceſſive Feat &amp; Zeal they pretend, is only to heighten Jealouſies among his Majeſties Subjects beyond all Prudence and Reaſon. It Non-conformiſts were in earneſt, why do they not run into the Arms of our Church which has been always open and ready to embrace them? for that's the only means to make Proteſtant Strength more Formidable. By this means we ſhould be able to oppoſe the Pope, and the Gates of Hell too: If they did this, there might be ſome credit given to their zeal: But can a conſidering man believe that they can poſſibly fancy Popery ſuch a dreadful thing and ſo unavoidably almoſt tumbling upon us; That they have ſo great a fondneſs for the Proteſtant Intereſt, &amp; that now they deem it in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of Danger, and yet will not make this one eaſy and certain ſtep to diſſipate that Threatning Cloud, and to increaſe the Strength, Intereſt and Reputation of the Proteſtant Cauſe: Surely theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Fears they expreſs, are feigned, or they had rather Popery ſhound come in than they themſelves ſhould conform to our preſent Churches; which ever of theſe it be the Government had need look wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to them. Our third Inquity is, Whether Phanaticks are the only Perſons that are truely zealous for protection of the preſent Government. The Romiſh Prieſts did not make, nor does increaſe them for that purpoſe. And we have found them continually owning and practiſiing Principles deſtructive to our envied Government. So then in King <hi>Jame</hi> his time writing to the Lord <hi>Hamilton</hi> to invite him to be their General; they told him the People were animated by the Word and Motion of God's Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to go to Arms: See them in <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt's time, making the whole Kingdom a Bloody Theatre, and to groan under all the heavieſt calamitous preſſures that the moſt miſerable diſtreſſed Nation could poſſibly be ſubject to: All backwardneſs in Murders, Rebellion and Robberies was then branded with Lukewarmneſs in the Cauſe of God: And <hi>Curſe ye Meroz</hi> &amp;c. Was thundred out againſt lots for God. <hi>Then the bleſſed Covenant was entred into: That we ſhall endeavour the extirpation of Prelates,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſhall not ſuffer our ſelves directly or indirectly by whatſoever Combination, Perſwaſion or Terrour to be divided and withdrawn from the bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Conjunction, whether to make defection on the contrary part, or to give our ſelves to a deteſtable Indifferency or Neutrality in the Cauſe,</hi> &amp;.c. <hi>But ſhall all the dayes of our Lives zealouſly and conſtantly continue therein againſt all opposition, and promote the ſame according to our Power againſt all Lets and Impediments whatſoever.</hi> And what Signs? what Indication have they given of Repentance for the Commiſſion of theſe helliſh Tragedies? or that they do not believe this Covenant, this bleſſed Union as they term it, Obligatory. No other than that they have drawn the Sword in <hi>Scotland,</hi> than that they have brought us, even us, who have ſo lately, ſo ſeverely ſmarted into a Relapſe of Faction, Parties and Confuſion, than that they live in perpetual contempt and non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity to what they have Covenanted againſt. Certainly therefore their hot pretended care for the preſent Government is but to terrifie the People with a greater danger than really there is. Thus I have demonſtrated that Phanaticks are in earneſt for nothing but Rebellion even by their moſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and popular pretences, I need not therefore trouble my ſelf to ſhew their more open impudence tends thereto; Such as Treaſonable Pamphlets againſt the King, Such as Libelling of the Government, Such as vilifying of the Clergy which was the ſecond way I obſerved they daily take to alienate the Affections of His Majeſties People and ſtir them up to Rebellion, and yet in ſuch Caſes 'tis difficult to depoſe againſt particular Perſons. I ſhall preſent you with one ſmart Example only and conclude; Who the Author of the Character of the Popiſh Succeſſor is I know not, therefore cannot depoſe againſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94823:5"/>him; But this I know, He deſerves ſevere puniſhment for the great pains he has taken to propagate Rebellious Principles. This man is the Darling of the Phanaticks, and he ſpeaks downright in terms for Rebellion, for which Reaſon I quote him rather than another, tho' at the very naming of him I begin to be in a ſweat; for you muſt know Reader, it is a Plaguy thing this hot Weather to be tumbling over a huge Company of great rumbling words without one dram of Senſe for ones refreſhment. Therefore take it kindly that I ſhew you this thundring Fellow; And ſtand clear here how be comes. p. 8. <hi>The Judges, Sheriffs, Juſtices of Peace, and all the Judicious Officers are of the Kings Creation: But if the Publick Miniſters of Juſtice betray the Liberties of the Subject, the Subject may peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a Parliament to Puniſh them for't. But what if he will neither hear one, nor call the other? Who ſhall compell him?</hi> Good God! Here's a Rogue thinks I to my ſelf; He has taught the King to make us all Slaves whether we will or no; S'bud we muſt all doff our Dublets, and away to making of Bricks without allowance of Straw: But Mr. Charactarizer, ſince you are ſo good at invention, can you find out no trick to prevent this Deviliſh thing? No; there's no way but a Parliament? and what if he won't call one, who ſhall compell him? That's true, no body can compell him as I know on: but hang't I ſhall fair as well as the reſt: Getting a little life at this thought (tho it did ſtick confoundedly in my Maw that the Fool did not keep private to himſelf this eaſy way of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Kings of <hi>England</hi> Arbitrary) on I went with my reading, but found a tormenting deal of Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh in my way, ſometimes as I was telling you over head and ears pop't I amongſt a great heap of empty words, ſometimes faſt ſtuck between contradictions; at laſt puffing and blowing I came to p. 20. where I met with this crum of Comfort: <hi>There's ſcarce a Precedent in the oldeſt Hiſtorical part of the Bible, that ſhall not by an extorted application be appropriated even to the duty and neceſſity of all ages, places and conſtitutions of the World, for example they'l tell you the Prophet</hi> Samuel <hi>makes the anſwer to the Jews that deſired a King, that he would make their Sons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and you ſhall cry out in that day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of your King that ye have choſen; which was as much as if the Prophet had ſaid; If a King ſhall (as he may do this) you have no redreſs but to your Prayers for his converſion. He does not tell them they might Revolt or Rebell to Redreſs themſelves: No, Heaven forbid he ſhould; for their King was abſolute,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Here indeed a paſſive Obedience is due; But what's this to a King of</hi> England? Say you ſo quot hI? then given me my Whinyard, I'm reſolved to have a bruſh for 't before I come to the making Bricks; for it ſeems if we think a King of <hi>England</hi> intrenches upon our Liberties and Properties, we may Revolt and Rebell, to Redreſs our ſelves: All places in Scripture which teach obedience to Princes in ſuch caſes are appropriated to us by extorted applications. Now, Reader, if you ſhould object, as 't is very likely you may. <hi>First,</hi> How it comes to paſs that no body could Rebell? In p. 8. But that every Body may Rebell in p. 20. That there was no Redreſs in p. 8. but Prayers for a Parliament: and if the King would not call one, no body could compell him: But that in p. 20. Prayers for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs are proper only for Subjects of abſolute Princes, But all that's nothing, to a King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> we need not pray for the turning of his heart, but turn all the Kings of <hi>England</hi> as <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt was turned. My ſolution to this objection is in p. 8. The Peoples conditions were to be made inevitably miſerable, they muſt not be allowed the leaſt hopes of Redreſs, that the Remedy of Rebellion, when't was offered, might be the ſweeter and more greedily received. <hi>Secondly,</hi> If you ſhould object how this doctrine of taking up Arms is reconcilable to the Statute of the 14. of this King, Chap. 3. which ſaith, <hi>For as much as within all his Majeſties Realms and Dominions the ſole and Supreme Power, Government, Command and Diſpoſition of the Militia, and of all Forces by Sea and Land, and of all Forts and Places of Strength is, and by the Laws of</hi> England, <hi>ever was the undoubted Right of His Majeſty</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and that both or either of the Houſes of Parliament cannot, nor ought to pretend to the ſame nor can, nor lawfully may raiſe, or levy any War, Offenſive or Defenſſive againſt His Majeſty His Heires, &amp;c.</hi> I have no other ſolution than as <hi>Ben Johnſon</hi> told us there were three ſort of Lights; So I tell you there are three ſorts of Wars, 1ſt. War Offenſive. 2. War Defenſive. 3. No War at all. Now tho' the two firſt Wars are mentioned in the Act, you know the Laſt is not, <hi>Ergo:</hi> So far I have manag'd well enough, but the next page does wonderfully gravel me. <hi>And if now at laſt Popery muſt and ſhall come in (as by Law it cannot) it muſt be reſtored by Arbitrary Power: if a new Monarchy, then a new Conqueſt. and if a Conqueſt, Heaven forbid we ſhould be ſubdued like leſs than</hi> Engliſh-<hi>men, or be debarr'd the common Right of all Nations, which is to Reſiſt or Repell an Invader, if we can,</hi> This juſtifies all the Plots, Conſpiracies and Rebellions of the Papiſts, for if Proteſtaniſm could not be brought-in by Law (as it could not, for the ſame reaſon Popery cannot) conſequently by Arbitrary Power: If a new Monarchy, then a new Conqueſt; and if a Conqueſt, Heaven forbid they ſhould be ſubdued like leſs then <hi>Engliſh</hi> men; or be debarr'd the Common Right of all Nations, which is to Reſiſt or Repell an Invader if they can: To be ſerious can there be greater impudence for a Fellow whoſeignorance fits him for a Schoolmaſters Laſh, with the help only of a hard Forehead and a few words borrowed out of ſome bombaſt Heroick Poem to dare to lay down Principles that juſtifie all Popiſh Plots and Conſpiracies; Principles of Rebellion which run exactly Counter to an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: And yet all this is humbly offered to the Parliaments conſideration! Als! Theſe men can't write againſt an Act of Parliament, They don't deſign Rebellion; for ſhame for ſhame let us ſee our Temporal as well Spiritual Intereſt loudly, and haſtily call us to be quiet and united, to be good Chriſtians and Loyal Subjects.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, Printed by</hi> N. Thompſon. 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
